Finding Aid for Austin W. Curtis Papers 1896-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Austin W. Curtis Papers 1896-1971
Curtis, Austin W., 1911-
1 oversize folders
1 oversize volumes
2 linear feet
Assistant to George Washington Carver at Tuskegee Institute, later a Detroit, Michigan, businessman. Correspondence and other papers of G. W. Carver relating primarily to experiments with soil improvement and the discovery of new applications for the peanut and other Southern agricultural products; newspaper clippings and memos relating to Curtis' campaign for Congress in 1958 and his work with Carver; and photographs.
851314;Aa;2;AC;Ac
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received from Austin W. Curtis (donor no. 5161 ) in 1971.
The collection is open for research.
Austin W. Curtis was a laboratory assistant to George Washington Carver at Tuskegee Institute. Later, he became a Detroit, Michigan businessman.
The Curtis collection has two parts: papers of George Washington Carver that Curtis collected while in Carver's employ; and papers of Curtis mainly relating to his business activities with A.W. Curtis Laboratories of Detroit, Michigan, and also his unsuccessful campaign for Congress in 1958. The Carver papers are of the most significance, relating to Carver's experiments with soil improvement and his discovery of new applications for the peanut and other agricultural products of the South.
Subjects:
A. W. Curtis Laboratories (Detroit, Mich.); African Americans.; African Americans--Michigan.; Agriculture--United States.; Bentley, Alvin M. (Alvin Morell), 1918-1969.; Curtis, Austin W., 1911-; Detroit (Mich.); Negro Manufacturers and Distributors Association.; Scientists--United States.; Southern states.; Tuskegee Institute.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1958.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1960.; United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.
Subjects - Visual Material:
African Americans.; Alabama.; Carver, George Washington, 1864?-1943.; Ford, Edsel, 1893-1943.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; George Washington Carver School (Ways, Ga.); Georgia.; Henry Ford Museum and Greenfield Village.; Laboratories.; Louis, Joe, 1914-1981.; Motion picture theatres--Virginia--Norfolk.; Starr, Floyd Elliot, 1883-1980.; Starr Commonwealth for Boys.; Tuskegee Institute.
Contributors:
Bethune, Mary McLeod, 1875-1955.; Caliver, Ambrose, 1894-1962.; Carver, George Washington, 1864?-1943.; Chisholm, Frank P.; Collingwood, Herbert W. (Herbert Winslow), 1857-1927.; Commission on Interracial Cooperation.; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963.; Dudley, James Benson, 1859-1925.; Earle, Franklin Sumner, 1856-1929.; Graves, Bibb, 1873-1942.; Hamilton, John, 1843-1921.; Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.; Morse, Warner Jackson, 1872-1931.; Moton, Robert Russa, 1867-1940.; National Pecan Growers Exchange.; Peabody, George Foster, 1852-1938.; Rosenwald, Julius, 1862-1932.; Spillman, William Jasper, 1863-1931.; Thomas, Jesse O.; Washington, Margaret James Murray, 1861-1925.; White, Walter Francis, 1893-1955.; Wilson, James, 1835-1920.
Genre/Form:
Drawings.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Business and personal papers
  - Correspondence undated, 1901-1942, 15 folders (Box 1)
  - Scientific correspondence and notes concerning mycological specimen 1900-1901, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Radio scripts (Box 1)
  - Bible class materials 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - George W. Carver miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning George W. Carver 1896-1971, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Low-cost paint experiments 1939-1942, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Research proposals 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning Haitian business plan 1955 (Box 1)
  - Report of investment and business potential of the Republic of Liberia, West Africa (Box 1)
  - Curtis's campaign for Congress 1958 (Box 1)
  - Reports of field work on behalf of the senatorial campaign of Alvin M. Bentley 1960 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning A.W. Curtis, Jr. 1935-1965, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Negro Manufacturers and Distributors Association (Curtis was president) 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - A.W. Curtis Laboratories, Detroit, Michigan
    - Organization prospectus and suggestions for organized office operations (Box 2)
    - Literature for dealers (Box 2)
    - Form letters; price lists (Box 2)
  - Outline for comprehensive peanut research 1940 (Box 2)
    (report compiled by AWC at Tuskegee Institute)
  - Notebook concerning food laboratory report and Carver's visit to Henry Ford's food experimental laboratory in Dearborn, Michigan 1942 (Box 2)
  - George Washington Carver Foundation undated (Box 2)
  - George Washington Carver classbook circa 1897-1910 (Box 2)
  - George Washington Carver and Tuskegee Institute, 4 folders (Box 2)
    Includes pamphlets, reprints, brochures, and other printed materials
  - Notebook concerning plan for establishing the Carver Creative Research Laboratories at Tuskegee Institute 1937 (Volume 1)
    (prepared by A.W.Curtis, Jr.; includes photographs; 1 oversize volume: AC)
- Visual Materials (photographs and reproductions of photographs)
  The Visual materials series consists of photographs relating to the life and activities of George Washington Carver. Included are photographs of Carver, alone and with various notables; photographs of Carver's visit to Greenfield Village and to the Starr Commonwealth for Boys; photographs and reproductions of Tuskeegee Institute; and photographs of various buildings named in Carver's honor. In addition, there is a videotape (VHS) of Detroit Black Journal (Detroit television program) segment on Curtis (1990s?).
  - Portraits (also informal photographs of George Washington Carver) (Box 2)
  - George Washington Carver with others (Box 2)
    (receiving honorary degree; also with Joe Louis, Franklin Roosevelt, James A. Farley)
  - George Washington Carver with Atlanta businessmen alongside Georgia Railroad car (Box 2)
  - Henry Ford visiting Tuskegee Institute;George Washington Carver visiting Greenfield Village in Dearborn (Box 2)
  - George Washington Carver visiting the Starr Commonwealth for Boys in Albion, Michigan (Box 2)
  - Tuskegee Institute
    - Buildings, 2 envelopes (Box 2)
    - Laboratories (Box 2)
  - Carver Theatre (Norfolk, Virginia) (Box 2)
  - Carver School on the Ford Plantation, Ways, Georgia (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Videotape (VHS) of Detroit Black Journal segment on Curtis, 1990s (Box 2)
  - Photographs; watercolor studies made by George Washington Carver at Iowa State College Experiment Station (Folder 1)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Bethune, Mary McLeod, 1875-1955.
Mar. 14, 1925, Mar. 29, 1926
Caliver, Ambrose, 1894-1962.
Dec. 4, 1925
Carver, George Washington, 1864?-1943.
Correspondence throughout
Chisholm, Frank P.
Aug. 17, 1917, Sept. 29, 1917, Oct. 10, 1917, July 2, 1918, Oct. 11, 1918, Mar. 27, 1919, Dec. 9, 1924, Feb. 15, 1926
Collingwood, Herbert W. (Herbert Winslow), 1857-1927.
June 6, 1918, Dec. 9, 1924
Commission on Interracial Cooperation.
Nov. 17, 1924, Dec. 3, 1925, Nov. 16, 1926
Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963.
June 29, 1923
Dudley, James Benson, 1859-1925.
Mar. 1919
Earle, Franklin Sumner, 1856-1929.
Feb. 23, 1901
Graves, Bibb, 1873-1942.
Dec. 17, 1928
Hamilton, John, 1843-1921.
Dec. 30, 1905, Feb. 15, 1911
Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.
Sept. 11, 1919, Sept. 5, 1920, 1926
Morse, Warner Jackson, 1872-1931.
Aug. 24, 1925
Moton, Robert Russa, 1867-1940.
Feb. 7, 1918
National Pecan Growers Exchange.
Dec. 29, 1924, Jan. 1, 1925, Aug. 30, 1928
Peabody, George Foster, 1852-1938.
May 3, 1934
Rosenwald, Julius, 1862-1932.
Aug. 11, 1921, Dec. 21, 1926
Spillman, William Jasper, 1863-1931.
Nov. 14, 1905
Thomas, Jesse O.
Sept. 22, 1919, Oct. 20, 1924
Washington, Margaret James Murray, 1861-1925.
Nov. 27, 1911
White, Walter Francis, 1893-1955.
June 1923
Wilson, James, 1835-1920.
Sept. 6, 1906, Oct. 4, 1907, Feb. 4, 1908, Sept. 1, 1908, Dec. 10, 1910